hello guys my name is China welcome back
to my say plus plus series so today
we're going to be talking about move
semantics this is probably like the
single most requested topic so I'm happy
that I'm finally getting to and today
we're gonna be more or less taking a
look at an introduction to what move
semantics is because it's a very complex
topic the basics is really simple but
then what you can do with it and how it
works in practice we'll get to that
stuff don't worry so first of all make
sure that you've seen my Elle values and
our values video because this is more or
less going to be a continuation of that
video now that we've learnt what our
values actually are and what our value
references actually are we can take a
look at their single biggest use case
move semantics to keep things simple
move semantics essentially just allow us
to move objects around and this wasn't
possible before C++ 11 because C++ 11
introduced our value references which
are necessary for move semantics the
basic idea is that when we're writing a
C++ code there are a lot of cases in
which we don't really need to or want to
necessarily copy an object from one
place to another but that's really the
only place that we can get it from one
place to another so for example if I'm
passing an object into a function that
then is going to take ownership of that
object I have no choice but to copy it
the same goes for when I want to return
an object from a function I still have
to create that object inside that actual
function and then actually return it
which means that again I'm copying that
data now I don't really like to use
return values as an example for this
because there is of course something
called return value optimization which
can kind of optimize that part of it and
make it less of a problem but with the
first example if I need to pass in an
object a new object that I'm
constructing into some kind of function
that takes ownership of it or whatever I
still need to unfortunately construct
like essentially a throwaway
object in the current stack frame
wherever I am and then copy it into the
function that I'm calling which which is
not ideal because I don't actually need
it here I need it there but I can't
construct it there because I need to
first construct it here and then pass it
in it becomes a huge mess and sure if
your object just consists of like a
couple of integers or something like
that then copying it is no big deal
but what if your object needs to like
heap allocate memory or something like
that
what if it's a string and if you need to
copy it well you need to create a
completely new heap allocation that's
not good that becomes a heavy object to
copy and that is exactly where move
semantics comes in if we can just move
the object instead of copying it then
our performance will be higher and I
promise you once we dive in and take a
look in a minute you'll see that this is
not nearly as difficult as it might seem
but first this video is sponsored by
Skillshare for those of you who don't
know what Skillshare Skillshare is an
online learning community where millions
of creative and curious people can come
together to take the next step in their
creative journey they've got thousands
of amazing classes for you guys to check
out and the best thing is they're so
small and bite-sized and efficient that
even if you're super busy like I am
you'll still find the time to learn
something new which of course is always
important some of my personal favorite
classes on Skillshare are the
illustration and art related classes but
recently I found that they also have a
number of excellent productivity related
classes and I think that boosting your
productivity is both one of the hardest
and most rewarding things to do so
definitely check them out and starting
at less than $10 per month for an annual
subscription I think it's really great
value but if you guys want to check out
a two month free trial then you can by
clicking a link in description below
huge thank you again to Skillshare for
sponsoring this video
sir move semantics let's dive in and
take a look at what all the fuss is
about let's write a class that's going
to serve as an example to demonstrate
why exactly we might want to move
something so I'm just going to write a
very basic string class that might look
something like this this is not by any
means going to be like a proper way to
write a string class in fact I might
make a video on that sometime in the
future but let's just say that we have a
class which has a char pointer of data
as well as some kind of size this is our
actual string data so what we want to do
here when we take in a Const our pointer
like this is essentially set the size to
be the string length so whatever the
length of this string is that's how many
characters we might want we probably
want a null termination character as
well but we'll just skip that for the
purposes of this example because again
this is about move semantics and not
necessarily about how to write a proper
string class and then into here I'll
just do a basic mem copy to move all of
the data in from the source string here
into our data buffer so now that we have
that and I'll actually just add a printf
here we
just says created just so that we can
later visualize our kind of code flow so
we have a basic constructor here that
takes in a string and allocates memory
and copies everything into that memory
buffer now inside the destructor we
might have something fairly simple to
just simply deletes the data and that's
that's about it that's our basic string
class now let's write some other class
for example maybe I'll call it entity
that's basically just going to consume
our string so inside the entity class I
might just have like a standard kind of
con string reference here maybe this
will be like the name of our entity and
then obviously we will store this so
I'll just write string m name here and
then I will simply just assign it like
this so at the moment for this to
actually work properly we need to write
a copy constructor because if we just
simply create a string over here or in
fact let's go the easy whale to say
entity entity and then maybe call it
churner like this and we're using the
implicit constructor here so really
what's happening is that and I might
leave it like that for clarity but
basically if we're if we just have some
code like this we still need some way of
copying this string into this string and
so we need a copy constructor so what
I'll do is I'll write a copy constructor
here and this copy constructor is going
to be very similar to this constructor
I'll copy it in fact I'll just change
this to copy it except obviously the
size is just going to be other dot size
and then everything else is pretty much
the same except of course we just write
other dot M data so now we're just
copying the string and we have a valid
way to actually get it in here if I run
this code in fact let's do one more
thing let's just write a function called
print name here and then that needs some
way of printing the name which we can't
actually do at the moment
so let's write a very basic function
here called print now because our string
class is special and doesn't have a null
termination character what I'll actually
do is loop through the size of the
string and then print each character one
by one sefa char and then we'll do M
data I and then at the very end I will
just print a new line character so now
this will just call m named print and we
should have a very basic program now
that will just basically just print
shown and if I run this code you can see
that we have created copied and Cherno
so everything is in fact working however
this is really the problem that
addressing today we have this copied
line being printed which of course means
that our data has been copied now why is
this a problem well the reason it's a
problem is because you can see that to
copy a string we need to allocate memory
on the heap we have to call new char
that's not that's not a good thing it's
definitely not terrible and especially
if you have just one copy like that let
me just quickly add this thing in here
as well it's not necessarily like the
worst thing in the world but remember
the fact that we have to copy this is a
little bit ridiculous because I mean
look at look at what we're doing we're
essentially creating an entity called
Cherno here and I mean we just need some
way of getting the string into here and
what does that do well that that has to
allocate memory twice because we need to
create it first in the scope of this
function inside our main function
which is what happens over here we're
actually creating it inside the main
function and then we're passing it into
this entity constructor which then on
this line over here has to actually copy
it into here why can't we just move it
into here why can't we just allocate the
memory right here and just have it there
or I mean worst case scenario because we
can't really do that without getting
access to the string and then doing
stuff like that manually why can't we
just still allocate it here in the main
function but then just move it into this
space because now we wanted to occupy
this space and the answer is of course
we can and that's where move semantics
comes in so what we need to do in this
case is write a move constructor so this
is very similar to the copy constructor
except this takes in our value reference
meaning a temporary so this right here
is a temporary it's not an L value is
not assigned to anything it's just used
up as a parameter for this actual entity
constructor so now by specifying this
constructor which by the way we should
specify with no except I mean even
visual studio is telling us because it's
not really supposed to be throwing
exceptions not that we really use them
anyway but just to be ultra correct
we'll do that and by specifying this
constructor the hope is that eventually
when we actually perform this copy
instead of copying it will actually move
now in order for that to actually work
we need to also make sure that entity
has a constructor that takes in a
temporary so instead of kind of doing
that what I'll do is I'll actually copy
and paste this constructor so I'll just
add a new constructor that takes in a
temporary like this now hope
course is that when we actually call
this because now that now that this is a
temporary and we're providing an R value
reference constructor since this is an R
value it will actually call this
constructor now instead of this
constructor now they are both the same
they do the same thing that is assigned
name the same way so nothing will change
but that's kind of the first step so now
we need to actually implement our move
constructor so what I'll do is I'll copy
in fact I'll just copy everything and
I'll show you how to do this
so we'll say moved over here size still
gets copied the same way and what we'll
do is we'll actually copy data but what
we're doing here is instead of actually
allocating a new buffer of data and
copying everything individually copying
copying that entire block of data into
this new block of data what we're doing
instead is we're simply assigning the
pointer so we're taking the pointer to M
data which is the pointer to the
existing buffer that we had in our
original string and now we're saying
that this pointer that we have here in
this new string instance that we've
constructed it actually points to the
same data so instead of allocating an
entire new block of data and copying
everything into it
we're just essentially pointing to the
same block of data as the old string now
this immediately presents a problem
because we do still have to string
instances so what happens to the old one
when it gets deleted well it's going to
take the data with us so what should we
do and that's exactly why I move
constructor cannot end right here you
have to also take care of the other
string the other string instance who
you're basically taking control over
you're stealing all of that data so to
do that we need to also assign m data to
null pointer that's kind of the the
major thing that we need to do but also
what we should do is assign size to be 0
so by doing so we've basically created
something called a hollow object this
old string is now essentially just in an
kind of like an empty state and what
will happen is when the old string
instance gets destroyed this delete m
data will actually be deleting null
pointer and obviously deleting null
pointer just doesn't do anything because
there's nothing to delete that pointer
is pointing to null so we've effectively
just taken over that old string instead
of doing a deep copy by copying all the
data and allocating new memory we've
essentially done as a shallow copy we've
just kind of rewired the pointers so now
everything should be good right let's
run this and see what we get and
you can see that interestingly we have
created copied destroyed and Cherno so
interestingly the Cherno is being
printed after destroyed because that's
actually our temporary getting destroy
so that seems to a function this didn't
crash or anything however we still have
a copied which is a little bit odd
because you know I mean we provided this
constructor what's going on and the
final answer is that what's actually
happening is the copy constructor is
still being called over here when we
actually assign name like this it's
actually still using this constructor to
get it to use the move constructor you
have to actually explicitly cast it to a
temporary like this and if we run this
code you'll see that we have a moved now
instead of copies so we've successfully
only allocated memory once and managed
to move the string into the entity class
now in practice you wouldn't really cast
it to an r-value reference like this
instead you would use something called
STD move which essentially does the same
thing
but we'll have an entire video on STD
move and all the stuff that's used for
in the future so let's run this code and
you can see that we still have the same
result created moved destroyed and then
we've managed to print our string
successfully everything it seems to run
so the the major point of this is that
we've saved using this copy constructor
to actually allocate a new block of
memory and copy it we've simply managed
to move that instead so we still only
have a single allocation which is great
okay so I hope that that was somewhat of
a good introduction to move semantics of
course there are so many more things we
could cover such as SCE move and don't
worry we will in future videos but I
hope you guys enjoyed this video if you
did please hit that like button don't
forget that you can try our Skillshare
free for two months by clicking the link
in the description below and I will see
you guys later
good bye
[Music]